<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practice of repentance. Or A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the fifteenth of September last passed, by Radford Mavericke, preacher of Gods word in Devon</title>
            <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1560 or 61.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841683</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841683</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practice of repentance. Or A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the fifteenth of September last passed, by Radford Mavericke, preacher of Gods word in Devon</title>
                  <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1560 or 61.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 18 misnumbered 19.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6281:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6281:1"/>
THE PRACTICE OF REPENTANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> A Sermon preached at PAVLS CROSSE, the fifteenth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember laſt paſſed,</p>
            <p>By RADFORD MAVERICKE, Preacher of Gods Word in DEVON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IER. 17. 21.</bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, Take heede to your ſoules.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6281:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6281:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honorable</hi> THOMAS, <hi>Lord RIDGEWAY, Baron of GALTEN-RIDGEWAY: And to the right Vertuous and Religious LADY his WIFE, all grace and happineſſe in Earth, accompanyed with all glorie and renowne in Heauen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONORABLE PERSONAGES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe you to peruſe theſe printed Papers, contayning the ſumme of a Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the Croſſe, not long ſithence, the Printer perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it onward with this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for that a Sermon touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Repentance, being preached at the ſame place now twentie yeeres gone, he thought it not meete that this preſent Sermon, perſwading vnto the practice of Repentance, and being ſo neere of
<pb facs="tcp:6281:3"/>
Kinne to the other, both in reſpect of the Author and Subiect, ſhould ſleepe in the graue of ſilence or obliuion, but rather taking her elder Siſter by the hand, ſhould ſeeke their fortunes in the wide Wilderneſſe of this World, where happily ſome godly diſpoſed will either for pitty, or pieties ſake, giue them intertaynement.</p>
            <p>And for mine owne part, this benefit I hope may redound by the printing of it, that as it may be with farre greater eaſe read and peruſed of them that heard it, then at that time it could well be attended vnto, by reaſon the winde was ſomwhat high and hard at the publiſhing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo ſuch as were not preſent may by this means be made partaker of the ſame both for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort: the mayne point therein handled, being a doctrine ſo neceſſary and generall, that it concernes all perſons and people whoſoeuer, that either long for, or deſire their eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>And now (Honorables) I will not ſpend ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wordes to yeeld reaſons or cauſes of this my Dedication to your honored ſelues; you are not ignorant that my ancient and long acquaintance, with you, (with reuerence I ſpeake it) here in your owne Country, and the certayne knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:6281:3"/>
I tooke of your zealous and pious courſes you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer held in the right path of Religion, (which happily hath prepared you for theſe greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Places) were motiues enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me to ſuffer theſe lines (if they had beene written with gold) to paſſe vnder your godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, to ſpeake nothing of the many fauours I haue receiued from you and your worthy Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which as I may neuer forget, ſo I take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with all thankefulneſſe often to remember them. One thing more I muſt adde, and ſo I end; at my being in London when this Sermon was preached, ſome few dayes before I promiſed your brother and verily intended to ſhew my dutie vnto you at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> when my paynes had beene ended about the ſame; but I was hindred only by ſickneſſe and weakeneſſe, which made me to returne home ſpeedily, where I thanke God, I haue now (after a long ſickneſſe) reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably well recouered my health and ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and am not altogether without hope, but that I may ſee you once more before I goe hence and be no more ſeene. Meane while and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I will not ceaſe to pray for your Honors prosperitie, both in your honored ſelues and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Progenie, that as God of his goodneſſe hath
<pb facs="tcp:6281:4"/>
aduanced you to theſe earthly Honors, which you know are but fading, ſo you may ſeeke by all meanes poſsible, to aduance Gods glorie in the Goſpell of his Sonne, and the true Profeſſors thereof, which ſhall be the Churches good, and your glorie for euer. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my poore houſe at ILSINGTON in DEVON,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the ſixt of AVGVST. 1617.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honors euer in the Lord to be commanded, RADFORD MAVERICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6281:4"/>
            <head>THE PRACTICE OF REPENTANCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IEREM. 4. 14.</bibl>
               <q>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued; how long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remayne within thee?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="exordium">
               <head>Exordium.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing this my Text ſeemeth to be but an  abrupt ſpeech of our Prophet, I ſhall the leſſe neede to be curious in obſeruing the Coherence of the ſame.<note place="margin">Coherence.</note> Yet being well  obſerued, we ſhall finde that it hath good dependency vpon the former part of this Chapter, where the Prophet biddeth <hi>Iſrael</hi> to returne to the Lord, and now ſheweth them how they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, by willing them to waſh their hearts from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſaying, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine heart, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="divisio">
               <head>Diuiſio.</head>
               <p>In which wordes, we may obſerue two generall parts:  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, an Exhortation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a Reprehenſion.</p>
               <p>An Exhortation to Repentance.</p>
               <p>The Reprehenſion, for that they linger ſo long their Repentance.</p>
               <p>The Exhortation in theſe wordes, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reprehenſion in theſe wordes, <hi>How long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remayne within thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6281:5"/>
In the exhortation I obſerue foure circumſtances.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Who exhorteth? <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Who are exhorted? The people of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Whereunto they are exhorted? To Repentance.</item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Wherefore? That they may be ſaued.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="exhortation" type="part">
               <div n="1" type="circumstance">
                  <p>Firſt then we are to conſider in the exhortation who exhorteth, namely <hi>Ieremie,</hi> one of the Lords Prophet, <hi>Excelſus Domino,</hi> one very highly beloued of the Lord, knowne vnto God before he was formed in the wombe, ſanctified in his Mothers belly, and ordayned to be a Prophet vnto Nations. For ſo it is read in the Text:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then the Word of the Lord came vnto me</hi> (ſaith Ieremie) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaying, Before I formed thee in the wombe, I knew thee, and before thou cameſt out of the wombe, I ſanctified thee, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned thee to be a Prophet vnto Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> Now, in that <hi>Ieremie</hi> is appointed and ordayned to be a Prophet vnto Nations, ſpecially vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> before he was borne, We are to obſerue therein, the care that  the Lord hath for the good of his Church and Children, long before, in prouiding for them, Paſtors &amp; Teachers, likewiſe Kings, Queenes, Captaynes, and Gouernours, who are nurſing Fathers, and nurſing Mothers, as well to  Church as Common-weale.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>
                     </label> So were <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> prouided, and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly  preſerued, for the deliuerance of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> before that, for the preſeruation of that  whole Family, which grew afterward into ſo great a Nation.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So was Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> and <hi>Mordecay</hi> preſerued from  the conſpiracy of that wicked <hi>Haman,</hi> for the great good of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were adiudged to the ſlaughter.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heſt.</hi> 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So was King <hi>Dauid</hi> preſerued firſt from the Lyon and  the Beare, and afterward from <hi>Goliah</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> that he might feed the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> prudently with all his power.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.37.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So was <hi>Ioſias, Hezechias,</hi> and other godly Kings: ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6281:5"/>
was <hi>Samuel</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets: ſo was <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, all prepared and prouided for the good of Gods Church as well of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So was that good and great King <hi>Conſtantine</hi> orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, to giue ſome breathing time to the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, after their ſo many and cruel perſecutions.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe we may ſay, was <hi>Iohn Huſſe, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prage, Martin Luther,</hi> and other godly Preachers, ſtirred vp and preſerued by Gods owne power, to oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the Pope, and to bring a new light, as it were, vnto the World.</p>
                  <p>So were many godly Biſhops and Preachers ſaued and preſerued in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> raigne, from the rage of that bloudy <hi>Bonner,</hi> and other cruell perſecuters.</p>
                  <p>So was our renowned Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (worthy of laſting memory, very ſtrangely and miraculouſly ſaued and preſerued at that time, when ſhee had often written her owne Epitaph, <hi>Tanquam Ouis,</hi> with her owne hand.</p>
                  <p>And to conclude (for of ſuch examples there is no end) who doth not ſee, and with all thankefulneſſe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the bleſſed prouidence of a gracious God, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing King <hi>Iames,</hi> our moſt gracious Soueraigne, from danger of death, euen before he was borne (as his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie confeſſeth in his ſpeech to the Parliament) from the point of the Dagger, before he was our King, and from many moſt vile Treaſons and Treacheries ſithence God gaue him vnto vs? (Not to name the Gunne-powder Treaſon for the horror thereof) and all this (doubtleſſe) if God make vs thankefull, for the euerlaſting good of thoſe Churches and Kingdomes, ouer whom Gods only prouidence hath placed him; whoſe grace guide him in all the pathes of pietie, and whoſe right hand ſhield him from all malignitie either of forraine or domeſticall foes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe that muſt be made hereof, is this, that whether he be a King or a Prince, a Prieſt or a Prophet, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer office wee haue either in Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6281:6"/>
we muſt know and acknowledge, that God hath aduanced each one to this or that place, that dignitie or this honor, onely or chiefly for the glory of his owne name, and for the ſpeciall good of his Church and Children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And we muſt all know farther, that no man commeth  into this world, by chance, but for ſome end and purpoſe, and that God doth ſet euery one his taske, allotting ſome ſpeciall dutie to euery one of his ſeruants, whereunto he ought ſpecially to attend.</p>
                  <p>This point is not vnneceſſary to be vrged in theſe dayes: but I cannot ſtand to inſiſt vpon it. Only this may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in particular, that becauſe our Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> was ſpecially and extraordinarily choſen and ordayned of God to ſo great and hard a taske, as to be oppoſite to the whole world, as it were, therefore God did extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily comfort and encourage him, as he did the reſt of his Prophets and Apoſtles; The ſame God, no doubt, it is, that to this day doth, and for euer will helpe and ſtrengthen the poore indeuours of all faithfull and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paſtors, that labour in the worke and Miniſterie of his Word, for the increaſe of your faith, the end whereof is the ſaluation of our ſoules.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the firſt circumſtance, who exhorteth, namely, <hi>Ieremie,</hi> a great Prophet of God, yet a man ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to many ſorrowes, and ſundry infirmities, as the beſt of Gods ſeruants euer haue beene, and euer ſhall be in this world.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="circumstance">
                  <head>The ſecond circumſtance.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond circumſtance is, VVho they are that are  exhorted. And I ſay, the people of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof, both King, Prieſt, and People, none excepted. But the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, <hi>O Ieruſalem!</hi> I anſwere, it is a figuratiue ſpeech, vſuall in the Scripture, <hi>Continens pro contento,</hi> naming the Citie for the Citizens therein contayned. In the Goſpell it is ſaid, that all <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> went out into the wilderneſſe, vnto <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> that is, the people of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And Chriſt ſaith,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6281:6"/>
                     <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent vnto thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now we know, it was not the Citie, but the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Citie, the Kings, the Prieſts, and the People, that killed the Prophets, and after that CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS the Prince of Prophets. Therefore by <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> is meant the people of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> like as by the world is meant the things and people of the world.</p>
                  <p>So then, it is the people of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that are here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to Repentance, notwithſtanding they were the peculiar people of God, and dwelt in the moſt famous Citie of the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> The leſſon that we may learne hereby is this, that no  place in the world can priuiledge any one from ſinne: for had not <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſinned, and grieuouſly ſinned, they ſhould not haue needed exhortation to Repentance, nor reprehenſion for not repenting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned in Paradiſe, the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſinned at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the Pope ſinneth at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Hermites in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, no change of place, but the gift of grace ſtayeth the courſe of ſinne: all men haue ſinned at all times, and in all places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> The vſes hereof may be: firſt, for reproofe againſt <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Semipelagians</hi> the Papiſts, which dreame I know not of what perfection, as though they had beene borne aboue the Moone, and had had no touch or taſte of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne and contagion: but this hereſie though it be ancient, needs no other confutation, then the common experience of all the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it may ſerue to teach vs all, to walke warily  and circumſpectly in euery place, becauſe we can come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to no place, but we ſhall meete with occaſions enow to entice vs vnto ſinne, which occaſions wee muſt auoide as much as poſſibly we may.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> A third vſe may teach all Paſtors and Preachers, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all meanes poſſible in this dutie, to conuince the world of ſinne, as Chriſt exhorteth, whereſoeuer they be placed.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6281:7"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> The fourth vſe may be for Magiſtrates, to learne them  to looke well about them, to haue their eyes in euery cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to ſeeke and finde out the tract and haunt of ſinners, to puniſh ſinne ſeuerely, when and where it is found; leſt it be ſaid vnto them, They haue borne the ſword in vaine. It was a ſage ſaying, Seeke not to be in authoritie, except thou canſt mightily put downe ſinne; the Sword and the Word ſhould goe together in this dutie.</p>
                  <p>A fifth vſe we might here inſert, that ſeeing <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> it ſelfe, nor any other Church or Kingdome in the world, is free from ſinne, and the pureſt Churches that euer were, had their many imperfections; therefore none ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate <note n="*" place="margin">Papiſts for <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Rhemes.</hi> Browniſts for <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
                     </note> themſelues from the ſocietie of the faithfull in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Church, State, or Kingdome, where Chriſt his Goſpel is purely preached, his Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, and good diſcipline eſtabliſhed, for the puniſhment of ſinne. And this doctrine will fall hard vpon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Recuſant <hi>Papists,</hi> that runne to <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Rhemes,</hi> as alſo vpon our <hi>Browniſts</hi> or Separatiſts whoſoeuer, that like <hi>Amſterdam</hi> better then <hi>England,</hi> haply becauſe it is better and fitter for their purpoſes.</p>
                  <trailer>And ſo much for the ſecond circumſtance.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="circumstance">
                  <head>The third Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</head>
                  <p>The third circumſtance, and which is moſt materiall, and therefore hath neede moſt to be ſtood vpon, is, The matter or thing wherevnto they are exhorted, and that is (doubtleſſe) vnto Repentance, a point very much vrged, but coldly practized.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> began with this doctrine, &amp; Chriſt the Son of God did ſecond him, ſaying, <hi>Repent: for the Kingdome of beauen is at hand: repent and beleeue the Gospell.</hi> This we know was alwayes the manner of the Prophets before that time, to call people to Repentance. And it was the firſt and chiefeſt point of doctrine, which the Apoſtles of Chriſt were commanded by our Sauiour to vrge after his Reſurrection, <hi>That Repentance and Remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould be preached in the name of</hi> IESVS, <hi>beginning at Ieruſalem:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.</note> Where our Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> propheſied long time before.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6281:7"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> But if <hi>Ieremies</hi> minde and purpoſe were to exhort the <hi>Iewes</hi> vnto Repentance, why doth he not vſe plaine words to perſwade thereunto?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> I anſwere, that this Metaphor of waſhing which our Prophet vſeth in this place, is farre more ſignificant, then if he had exhorted to Repentance in plaine termes. For now, in ſtead of one word which he might haue vſed, namely, <hi>Repent,</hi> he vſeth ſuch wordes, whereby they are both exhorted to Repentance, and alſo taught how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. We will therefore conſider the wordes in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and take them both for an exhortation, and as a dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Repentance: Only this one thing I would craue by the way of intreatie, that hereafter, in all this Sermon, you would not take theſe wordes of our Prophet any more as ſpoken to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but directed vnto vs: for whatſoeuer is written, you know, it is written for our learning. And as <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to whom this was firſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, was a type and figure of the Church of God, ſo doth this exhortation, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe,</hi> belong to all Churches and Kingdomes, Cities &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Nations and People, to all (I ſay) in generall, and to euery one in particular; euery one hath neede to haue his heart waſhed and clenſed from wickedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>So that now in this third circumſtance we muſt ſpeake  of three things.
<list>
                        <head>Three things.</head>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, of waſhing, or clenſing. </item>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, of waſhing or clenſing of the heart. </item>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, of vvaſhing or clenſing the heart from vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="point">
                     <head>And firſt, of vvaſhing or clenſing.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Note,</hi> Waſhing.</note>This Metaphor of vvaſhing, as it is very ſignificant, ſo  it is very vſuall among the Prophets.</p>
                     <p>The Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> vvhen he had moſt ſharply reproued the ſame Nation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> calling the Princes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Princes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and the People thereof, the People of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> vpbrayding them that they were a finnefull Nation, a People laden vvith iniquitie, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6281:8"/>
children, telling them plainely and peremptorily, that the whole head vvas ſicke, and the vvhole heart vvas heauy, that from the ſole of the foote, to the crowne of the head, there vvas no vvhole part, but vvounds and ſwellings and ſores of ſinne, full of corruption; and ſo proceedeth on with ſuch terrible menacings and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, as though the Lord had vtterly reiected them, and would neuer receiue Prayer or Oblation more at their hands; for it was a burthen vnto him. Yet on a ſudden, the Prophet changeth his ſpeech, and exhorteth them to Repentance, with theſe like vvordes of our Text, <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well, ſeeke iudgement, releeue the oppreſſed, iudge the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, and defend the widdow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>
                        </label> Where-hence I obſerue, that waſhing and clenſing are fit vvordes to expreſſe the nature of true Repentance: which thing alſo vvas plainely ſignified, by the diuers vvaſhings in the Leuiticall Law:<note place="margin">Leuiticall Law.</note> for ſuch indeede is the  nature of ſinne, before it be truely repented of, that it maketh man more vgly in the ſight of God, then the fouleſt Leper in the vvorld can be in the ſight of man.</p>
                     <p>And indeede, to ſpeake all in a vvord, ſinne is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Leproſie; and therefore if <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> had neede to vvaſh himſelfe ſeuen times in the floud of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> vvhich ſignifieth the Riuer of Iudgement, before the could be clenſed from his bodily Leproſie, how many times aboue ſeuentie times ſeuen times haue wee neede to be waſhed and clenſed from our ſpirituall Leproſie, which hath ſo taynted and ſoyled our bodies and ſoules; that all the vvater in <hi>Iordan</hi> is not able to clenſe one ſoule from this diſeaſe of ſinne; but only the bleſſed bloud of our ſweet Sauiour that was baptized in <hi>Iordan</hi> is it, that muſt clenſe vs from all ſinne!</p>
                     <p>For this cauſe Chriſt the true Phyſician of our ſoules, did of his gracious goodneſſe cure and clenſe many Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers from the filth of their bodies, that thereby he might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6281:8"/>
make knowne to the world, that it is he onely which was appointed by God to bee to the purgator and clenſer of our ſoules, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth: <hi>The bloud of Chriſt clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs from all ſinne.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.7.</note> And the ſame Apoſtle, in the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,  ſignifyeth vnto the ſeuen Churches, that it is Ieſus Chriſt <hi>which loued vs and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his bloud.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.5.</note> This cleanſing and waſhing of our ſins in the bloud  of Chriſt, was prefigured in that bloud of the <hi>Paſchall Lambe, wherewith the Doore poſtes of the children of Iſrael were ſtricken;<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.7.</note> And alſo in the bloud of thoſe ſacrifices, which</hi>  Aaron <hi>was to offer, part of the bloud whereof was to be put vpon the hornes of the Altar, with his finger, and the reſt of the bloud to be powred on the foote of the Altar.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.12.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many ſuch Ceremonies, and prefigurations are euery where to be read in the old Teſtament, the truth and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof was accompliſhed in the new. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore  Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaide well, The new Teſtament was wrapped vp in the olde, and the olde vnfolded in the new:<note place="margin">Nouum in vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri obuolutum, vetus in none explicatum.</note> All which are more plainely opened vnto vs by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where he ſheweth, <hi>that all things almoſt were by the Lawe purged by bloud, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſheading of bloud was no remiſſion.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.22.23.</note> And hee addeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>that it was neceſſary that the ſimilitude of heauenly things ſhould be purified by ſuch things, but that the heauenly things themſelues are purified with better ſacrifices then theſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreouer, <note place="margin">Iſaack.</note>
                        <hi>Iſaack,</hi> who was readie to be ſacrificed, was  a true figure of Chriſt, which was the ſubſtance that was ſacrificed for vs, being both Prieſt and ſacrifice, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe for our ſinnes vpon the Altar of the croſſe, his holy body, being the night before he ſuffered, waſhed all ouer with his owne moſt precious bloud, like as the high Prieſt was vſed to bee waſhed the night before hee came into <hi>Sancta Sanctorum.</hi> And his ſacred ſide, when he hung vpon the Croſſe, to the very piercing of his harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe heart, was opened with a ſpeare or launce. <hi>Vt pateant viſcera per vulnera</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſweetely) <hi>&amp; vt per foramina Corporis, pateant arcana cordis.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> That the bowels 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6281:9"/>
of Chriſts loue might appeare in his wounds, and that the ſecret ſweetneſſe of his heart towards vs might be ſhewed foorth through the windowes or holes of his body.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hence iſſued,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>both bloud and water:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.34.</note> bloud, becauſe without ſhedding of bloud there was no  remiſſion; water, to ſignifie the continuall waſhing of our ſinnes in the bloud of Chriſt. 

<q>
                           <bibl>1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. 5.</bibl>
                           <p>This is that Ieſus Chriſt, ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that came by water and bloud: not by water onely, but by water and bloud, and it is the Spirit that beareth witneſſe; for the Spirit is truth.</p>
                           <p>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> For there are three which beare record in heauen: The Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt; and theſe three are one.</p>
                           <p>And there are three which beare record in the earth: The Spirit, and Water, and Bloud; and theſe three agree in one.</p>
                           <p>If we receiue the witneſſe of men, the witneſſe of God is greater; for this is the witneſſe of God which hee teſtified of his Sonne:</p>
                           <p>He that beleeueth in the Sonne of God, hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, Hee that beleeueth not God, hath made him a lyer, becauſe hee beleeueth not the recorde which God witneſſed of his Sonne.</p>
                           <p>And this is the record, that God hath giuen vnto vs eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne.</p>
                           <p>He that hath the Sonne of God, hath life, and he that hath not the Soune of God, hath not life.</p>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Here (beloued) is life, here is water of life offered vnto vs. Ho, euery one that is athirſt, come,</hi> ſaith the Euangelical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>come buy without ſiluer</hi> (that will not the Pope doe,  he will not ſell his pardons without ſiluer:) but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, <hi>Come buy without money, without penny or pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie-worth.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay.</hi> 55.1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore it was that our Sauiour himſelfe cried out in the laſt and great day of the feaſt, <hi>If any man thirst, let him come vnto me and drinke;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7.37.</note> And likewiſe ſaith vnto the vvoman of Samaria,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John.</hi> 4.10.</note> 
                        <hi>If thou kneweſt the gift of God, and who it is that ſayeth vnto thee, Giue mee drinke, thou wouldest haue asked of him, and hee would haue giuen</hi>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6281:9"/>
                        <hi>thee water of life.</hi> And in the laſt of the Reuelation, <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come: and let him that heareth, ſay, Come: and let him that is athirſt come; and whoſoeuer will, let him take of the water of Life freely.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.17.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                        </label> Now to make vſe of all this, let vs call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, what the <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſaith vnto <hi>Philip</hi> in the eight of the <hi>Acts; See,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>here is water: What ſhould let me to be baptized? Philip</hi> anſwered, <hi>If thou beleeueſt with all thine heart, thou mayſt.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>So may you all ſay vnto me, beloued; Here you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vnto vs Water, and here you propoſe vnto vs wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Life: What ſhould let, that wee ſhould not bee ſaued?</p>
                     <p>I anſwere you all in generall, and euery one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, out of my Text, <hi>If thou waſh thine heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, thou mayeſt be ſaued.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou art a Chriſtian, and the badge of a Chriſtian is Baptiſme: As Water doth ſerue to waſh away the filth of thy body; ſo, the effect of Baptiſme is to waſh away the filth of thy ſoule.</p>
                     <p>Thou art buried by Baptiſme, into the death of Chriſt,  that like as Chriſt was rayſed vp by the glorie of the Father. ſo thou ſhouldeſt walke in newneſſe of life.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.</note> 

                        <q>
                           <bibl>1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</bibl>
                           <p>For Chriſt (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) hath once ſuffered for our ſinnes, the iuſt, for the vniuſt, to bring vs vnto God, and was put to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as concerning the fleſh, but was quickned in the Spirit. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> By which Spirit he alſo went and preached vnto the ſpirits that are in priſon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> which were in time paſſed diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, when once the long ſuffering of God abode in the dayes of Noah, while the Arke was preparing, wherein few, that is, eight ſoules, were ſaued in the water. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> To the which alſo the figure that now ſaueth vs, euen Baptiſme, agreeth (not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh, but in that a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience maketh requeſt to God) by the reſurrection of <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> from the dead.</p>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Alluſion. Gen.</hi> 7.</note>By which alluſion of the Apoſtle, it is nothing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure to be collected, that the water wherein <hi>Noah</hi> was 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6281:10"/>
ſaued, the Red Sea,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</note> and after, the Riuer <hi>Iordan,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through  the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſſed,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 3.</note> together with the  two Prophets <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
                        <note place="margin"> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 2 5.</note> whom S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Cyprian</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to Chriſt and Chriſtians, <hi>Elias</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>Eliſha</hi> to  Chriſtians. Alſo the Cloude which paſſed ouer the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the Wilderneſſe.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.</note> The waſhing of <hi>Naaman</hi> the  <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> the Poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.</note> theſe, all of them were types and figures of our Baptiſme, like as our Baptiſme is, and ſhould be vnto vs, a badge or token of our new Birth or Regeneration, that ſo, in the water of true Repentance, we ſhould daily waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe.</p>
                     <p>The which myſterie the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth make more plaine vnto vs, in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and tenth Chapter, where ſpeaking of the Fathers liuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the old Law, he ſaith, <hi>That they were all baptized vnto Moyſes in the cloude and in the Sea, and did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke of the ſame ſpirituall drinke</hi> (meaning with vs Chriſtians:) <hi>For they dranke</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the ſpirituall Rocke which followed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But as in many of theſe <hi>Iewes,</hi> God had no delight, ſo with many of vs Chriſtians that are baptized only, with the outward Water of Baptiſme, God is not pleaſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe together with the ſigne of Baptiſme, wee doe not care for the thing ſignified, that is, to waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> telleth vs, <hi>that Circumciſion</hi> vnto the Iewes,  <hi>was nothing: but the keeping of the Commandements of God;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>S. Paul. Rom</hi> 7.19.</note> What then can Baptiſme be vnto vs Chriſtians, but the waſhing away of our ſinnes in the bloud of Chriſt? Which thing we ſhall doe, if we truely repent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Goſpell, and bring forth fruits worthy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; daily and hourely labouring to waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe; As <hi>Dauid</hi> waſhed his Couch with weepings, and as <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> waſhed the feete of Chriſt with her teares; which was a true token of her vnfayned repentance.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6281:10"/>
                     <trailer>And thus much haue I ſpoken concerning waſhing or cleanſing.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="point">
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>2</label> Next, we muſt conſider, what muſt be waſhed, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our hearts, <hi>Cor pro anima &amp; ſenſu, acceptum.</hi> As the  Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rent your hearts, and not your garments:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So ſaith <hi>Ieremie</hi> here; <hi>Waſh your hearts and not your clothes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And a little before in this Chapter, he ſaith, <hi>Breake vp the fallow ground, and ſow not among thornes, be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Lord, and take away the foreskin of your hearts.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jerem.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.4.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The heart of Man, as ſome thinke, is the ſeate of the ſoule. And true Repentance indeed muſt be from the heart and ſoule; therefore God craueth that chiefely, <hi>My ſonne, giue me thine heart.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouerb.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But whether the heart or the braine of man be the ſeate of the ſoule, we will not diſpute; ſure I am, now the heart of man is the ſinke of ſinne, as our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Out of the heart proceede euill thoughts, Adulteries, Fornications, Murther, and the reſt.</hi> And God himſelfe who is the true <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and onely ſearcher of the heart, pronounceth, that <hi>the heart of man is euill continually.</hi> And our Prophet in another place affirmeth, that <hi>the heart of man is deceitfull of all other things: who can finde it out?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 17.9.</note> there are ſo many concauities and hollow places in the heart, ſo many hidings, and ſo many turnings, that it hath neede of a great deale of skill and care to cleanſe and waſh the ſame, and much filth is left behinde in ſecret fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, which we know not of: Inſomuch that he muſt be a very wiſe, carefull, and diligent Man, that can finde out but euen the corruption of his owne heart.</p>
                     <p>Hence is it that there are ſo many Hypocrites in the world, that hiding many foule and ſecret ſinnes in their hearts, can yet make ſhew to the world, that they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry holy and religious. Many men there are that deſire to be taken for godly and faithfull men; yet the queſtion may ſtill be demanded, Where ſhall one finde a faithfull man? ſuch a one as <hi>Nathaniel</hi> was: euen <hi>a true Iſraelite, in whom there is no guile.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6281:11"/>
                        <hi>Ieremie</hi> is commanded in the next Chapter to our Text, <hi>to runne too and fro by the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, and to enquire in the open places of the ſame, if he can finde a man that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth iudgement, and ſpeaketh the truth from his heart, that God might ſpare that Citie to puniſh it.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And in the two and twentieth Chapter of <hi>Ezechiel, God complayneth, that he ſought for a man among them, that ſhould make vp the hedge, and ſtand in the gap betwixt him and the Land, that he might not deſtroy the ſame, but could find none. Therefore, ſaith the Lord, haue I powred out mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vpon them, and conſumed them with the fire of my wrath, their owne wayes haue I rendred vpon their owne pates, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.30.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And it is greatly to be feared, how we ſhould fare, if the Lord ſhould looke downe from heauen vpon vs, that liue in this laſt age of the world, as he did vpon the old world a little before he deſtroyed it, to ſee the greatneſſe of the wickedneſſe of men vpon the earth, and that all the imaginations of mans heart are euill continually.</p>
                     <p>And who knoweth whether the Lord be ready to come out from heauen, or to ſend his Angels (becauſe the ſins of our Land are exceeding grieuous, and the crie thereof very great) to inquire whether we haue done altogether according to the crie that is euen aſcended to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, or no?</p>
                     <p>Let vs therefore (beloued) if we will haue any care to preuent the fierce wrath of the Lord, which is readie to fall vpon vs, returne ſpeedily vnto the Lord by true and vnfayned Repentance; or to vſe the wordes of our Text, <hi>Let vs waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe, that we may be ſaued.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                        </label> But <hi>Chriſt ſaith vnto Peter, He that is waſhed, needeth not ſaue to waſh his feete.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi> Ioh.</hi> 13. 10.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> I anſwere, that by feete there, is meant all our filthy  affections, which proceede from the heart of man: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Chriſt, <hi>to waſh our feete,</hi> and with <hi>Ieremie, to waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe,</hi> is all one.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6281:11"/>
The <hi>Iewes,</hi> about the time our Prophet preached this, and afterward, were very ceremonious and ſuperſtitious too in their waſhings; they thought and perſwaded themſelues, if they did or could obſerue the outward rites or cuſtomes of their Fathers, touching their eternall cleanſings and waſhings, it was well enough, nay rather very well. But <hi>Ieremie</hi> here wiſheth them to waſh their hearts, becauſe <hi>they drew neere vnto God with their mouthes, but their hearts were farre from him.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.13.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Our Sauiour himſelfe reproueth theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> very ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.</note> as we reade in the Goſpell, for this their hypocriſie, for that they were ouer-carefull to make cleane the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſide of the cup and platter, but their hearts were full of all rauening and wickedneſſe. Therefore wiſedome willeth vs to conſecrate our hearts vnto God. Not that God wil not haue the hand as wel as the heart, the worke as well as the vvill, the body as well as the ſoule, and all the members and faculties both of body and ſoule ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified vnto his ſeruice: As S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth, <hi>to giue our bodies a liuely ſacrifice vnto God:</hi> but becauſe the heart is the chiefeſt part, and the fountayne from whence all our thoughts, wordes, and workes doe ariſe: therefore the heart muſt firſt be waſhed and cleanſed, purified by faith in a good conſcience, to ſerue the liuing God: For if the fountayne be foule, the waters that iſſue from it, cannot be cleane. And as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith well, <hi>Deus magis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis intentionem, quàm actum operationis intendit:</hi> God doth more reſpect the intention of the heart, then the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worke whatſoeuer. Man iudgeth according to the outward appearance, but God ſeeth the heart. For he is the only ſearcher of the hearts and reynes. All things are naked before him. <hi>Can any hide himſelfe in ſecret places,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 23.24.</note> 
                        <hi>ſaith the Lord?</hi> He vnderſtandeth all thy pathes, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy priuy pathes of pride, of diſſimulation, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayning thy brother, of fornication, of couetouſneſſe, of briberie, theft, extortion, and the like, though acted by thee neuer ſo ſecretly. God ſaw and diſcouered <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans</hi>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6281:12"/>
vvedge of gold, though hid in his Tent; God ſaw <hi>Achab</hi> ſicke at the heart for <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard: God ſaw <hi>Geheſies</hi> heart, and made <hi>Eliſha</hi> to ſee him alſo, <hi>Did not my heart go with thee,</hi> ſaith the Prophet? that is, did not I ſee thee, when thou ranneſt after <hi>Naaman</hi> for a bribe?</p>
                     <p>God grant we haue not among vs too many <hi>Achans,</hi> too may <hi>Achabs,</hi> too many <hi>Geheſies,</hi> that couer many foule ſinnes, vnder their gownes or cloakes of hypocriſie, that make a goodly ſhew to the world that they are god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but their hearts are full of wickedneſſe; that waſh their hands cleane euery day, but their hearts ſcarce once in the yeere, ſcarce once by their liues, with the water of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: yet ſtill my text ſaith, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, Waſh thine heart.</hi> If Pilate had waſhed his heart, as cleane as he waſhed his handes, he would neuer haue condemned an Innocent to death, for feare of the people. The feare of man chaſed away the feare of God, as the Wiſeman ſaith: contrary wiſe, <hi>As the face of the King cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away euill from his Throne, ſo the feare of God driueth out wickedneſſe from the heart of man.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prou.</note> 
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                        </label> The vſe of all this is, to haue God and his feare alwayes before our eyes, ſo that what ſinne ſoeuer we are tempred to commit, wee may ſay with godly <hi>Ioſeph, How ſhall</hi> I <hi>commit this wickedneſſe, and ſo ſinne againſt God?</hi> Therefore the Scripture ſayth, <hi>Bleſſed is he that feareth alwayes.</hi> The wicked, all their care is to hide their ſinne from man; but the godly deſire alwaies to haue a good conſcience before God. I will conclude therefore this point with a ſingular ſentence of Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> fitting for this purpoſe:<note place="margin">Auſten.</note> 
                        <hi>Quum hoc diligeuter conſidero, Domine Deus meus, terribilis &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> When I conſider this matter well, (namely how God looketh into the inmoſt intention of our hearts) O Lord God (ſaith he) fearefull and terrible, <hi>Timore pariter, &amp; ingentirubore confundor:</hi> I am (ſayth hee) with feare and ſhame confounded, <hi>quoniam nobis magna eſt indita neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas iuſtè recte<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> viuendi:</hi> becauſe there is ſo great neceſſitie laid vpon vs to liue rightly and iuſtly, <hi>quia cuncta facimus</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6281:12"/>
                        <hi>ante oculos Iudicis cuncta cernentis:</hi> ſeeing whatſoeuer wee doe, or intend to doe, we doe the ſame before the eyes of our Iudge which ſeeth all things.</p>
                     <trailer>And ſo much alſo for the ſecond circumſtance: the waſhing of the heart.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="point">
                     <head>The third Circumſtance.</head>
                     <p> The third followeth to bee conſidered; From what we muſt waſh or cleanſe the heart, namely, from Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I truſt I ſhall not neede to inlarge my ſpeech very much vpon this point, ſeeing all our ſpeech hitherunto hath aymed at this, to teach vs <hi>to waſh our heartes from Wickedneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By wickedneſſe is meant in this place all ſinne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe whatſoeuer, that lyeth lurking in the heart of man. The Word which our Prophet vſeth, is <hi>Ragnah,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> which may ſignifie <hi>malum, malitia,</hi> or <hi>ira;</hi> Wrath, malice, or any wickedneſſe whatſoeuer, and ſo it is diuerſly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. <hi>Montanus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Laua:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>id eſt, a malitia cor tuum:</hi> Waſh thine heart from malice. <hi>Hierome</hi> and others ſay, <hi>Laua à malo cor tuum;</hi> that is, Waſh thine heart from euill. And agreeable to both is our tranſlation, <hi>Waſh thine heart from Wickedneſſe,</hi> from malice: Whereby the Fathers are wont to meane the malignitie or poyſon of ſinne; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, as I ſayd before, it may be taken for all ſinne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie whatſoeuer; yet becauſe nothing doth poyſon the heart of man more then malice and enuie, therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>But now put you away all theſe things, wrath, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, crying and euill ſpeaking farre from you, with all maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.38.</note> And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> likewiſe exhorteth to <hi>lay aſide all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe, and all guile, and all diſſimulation, and all enuie, and all euill ſpeaking, and as new borne babes, to deſire the ſincere milke of the Word, that wee might growe thereby vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> The ſumme of all is, and this is the vſe that wee muſt make of this point, as of the whole exhortation, to teach vs, that wee muſt make a conſcience of euery ſinne, and waſh our hearts by Faith and true Repentance, from all vngodlineſſe, not from one ſinne, or ſome ſinnes, but from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6281:13"/>
all ſinne, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I haue turned my feete from euery e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil way, and all falſe wayes I vtterly abhorre.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> Diſſimulatio pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> to diſſemble with man is a ſinne: to equiuocate, as Papiſts do in matters of Religion, is a double ſin; but there is no mocking with God: <hi>Non bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec tutum eſt ludere cum Sanctis:</hi> there is no dallying with Saints. Yet herein the moſt part of common Chriſtians deceiue themſelues, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that God is well pleaſed with them, yea &amp; beholding to them too, if they can containe themſelues within the liſts or compaſſe of common Chriſtians.</p>
                     <p>Some are of opinion, that if they frequent publike prayers, heare Sermons now and then, when they can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them, receiue the Sacrament once or twice a yeere at the moſt, though otherwiſe they bee giuen to many foule vices, as Swearing, Drinking, Whoring, Rayling, and the like; that then they may be taken indeed for good Chriſtians; notwithſtanding they are as farre from the purity of the Goſpel, as Popiſh Recuſants are from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Church.</p>
                     <p>Others are of opinion, that if they can giue themſelues but leyſure, either from their profits or pleaſures, to heare Sermons (if at leaſt the Preacher pleaſe them) though they neuer come to Prayers, they can couer their couetouſnes, and many other ſinnes vnder that mantle.</p>
                     <p>To be ſhort, I feare there be few liuing, which haue not ſome Darling ſinne or other, which they both couer and cocker: wherein they flatter themſelues, euen to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling of their owne ſoules. Let euery one therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine well his owne heart, as the Apoſtle exhorteth, and be a ſeuere officer in his owne houſe, leauing no corner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearched, and ſo labour by all meanes poſſible, to waſh and cleanſe his ovvne heart from Wickedneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                        </label> But heere may be obiected, that as it is not in man (as our Prophet ſaith elſevvhere) to direct his ovvne vvaies:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.23.</note> So is it not in man, to vvaſh or cleanſe his ovvn heart from  vvickednes, though he <hi>waſh himſelfe with Nytre, &amp; take vnto himſelfe much ſope,</hi> to vſe the vvords of the Prophet, in the  ſecond Chapter of this propheſie.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.22.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6281:13"/>
I anſwere by a diſtinction, that man muſt bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red either as he is regenerate, or not regenerate; as hee is vnregenerate, he can doe nothing in the worke of grace; but indeed as he is Regenerate, he is not altogether paſſiue in the workes of grace, as mortification, ſanctification, and the like; but actiue alſo and working together with Gods grace, who hauing renewed our wills, doth will vs and command vs to repent, to conuert, to turne, to worke out our ſaluation, to waſh our hearts from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and the like; and yet this doctrine is ſo farre from Poperie, as Poperie is from puritie or veritie it ſelfe; howbeit we muſt know, that euen this our working with God, is a ſpeciall worke of Gods Spirit working with vs and in vs, the great worke of our Regeneration. Therefore let Prayer and Repentance euer goe together; by true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance we muſt turne to the Lord, by Prayer we muſt craue grace to returne.</p>
                     <p>For this cauſe therefore, though our Prophet in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this fourth chapter exhort <hi>Iſrael</hi> to returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, yet after, hee betaketh himſelfe vnto prayer, ſaying, <hi>Turne thou vs, good Lord, and wee ſhall bee turned; conuert thou vs, good Lord, and we ſhall be conuerted.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore godly <hi>Dauid</hi> purpoſing true repentance, betaketh himſelfe to earneſt prayer, ſaying, <hi>Haue mercie vpon me, O God, according to thy louing kindneſſe, according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy compaſſion, put away mine iniquitie. Waſh mee throughly from mine iniquities, and cleanſe me from my ſinne. Purge me with Hyſope, and I ſhall be cleane, waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter then ſnow. Create in me a cleane heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heere beloued, is a perfect patterne for all poore Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, that ſobbe and ſigh for their ſinnes: to exhort them to often zealous and faithfull Prayer, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth euen with God, alſo to teach vs to whom we muſt direct our Prayers, namely, to the Lord onely, and not to Saint or Angel, as Popery teacheth, but true Religion tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6281:14"/>
but true Religion teacheth vs otherwiſe to pray to God, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, to waſh vs throughly from our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to clenſe vs from all our ſinnes: To purge vs with hyſſope, with which the bloud of the Paſchal Lambe was ſprinkled,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.22.</note> which muſt put vs in minde of the bloud of  Chriſt, which clenſeth vs from all ſinne. Then ſhall wee heare of Ioy and gladneſſe, when our hearts are bruiſed and broken for our ſinnes; for <hi>a broken and a contrite heart God doth not diſpiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore let vs ſeeke the Lord by faith and vnfayned Repentance, whiles he may be found; let vs call vpon him  by inſtant and hearty prayer, while hee is neere;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.6.</note> let the wicked forſake his wayes, and the vnrighteous his owne imaginations, and returne vnto the Lord, and he will haue mercie vpon vs, and to our God; for hee is very ready to forgiue. <note n="a" place="margin">Out of which Text I perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance out of this place twentie yeeres ſithence, and now praiſe God with all my heart, that hath yet lent vs ſo long a time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, praying fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie together with the ſpace, now to giue vs the grace tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to repent. <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                        </note> In a word; let vs all pray the Lord to <hi>waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe,</hi> that we may be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>And here I might very well end this part alſo, ſauing that there is one Maine point of doctrine more to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, which is, that as it is not ſufficient for a man to <hi>ceaſe from euill,</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh, but hee muſt alſo <hi>doe good:</hi> ſo it is not ſufficient for vs to pray the Lord to <hi>waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe,</hi> but alſo we muſt pray the Lord to fill our hearts againe with grace and goodneſſe: for that <hi>nullum vacuum</hi> in Philoſophie doth hold alſo in this point of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie: new wine muſt be put into new veſſels, they muſt not be left emptie.</p>
                     <p>Therefore when <hi>Dauid</hi> hath prayed GOD to <hi>create a new heart within him,</hi> he alſo prayeth to be renewed, that is, that his heart may be filled with a right ſpirit, that the ſpirit of ſinne and wickedneſſe being expelled, his heart may be filled with grace and goodneſſe; For the ſpirit of wickedneſſe may depart from a man for a time, but if the heart bee not preſently ſupplied with the good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace, <hi>the wicked ſpirit will quickely turne backe againe</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Luke 11.26.</note> (as our Sauiour teacheth vs) <hi>and enter into that man with</hi>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6281:14"/>
                        <hi>ſeuen worſe ſpirits then himſelfe, and ſo the end of that man ſhall be worſe then the beginning.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore I ſay, this point muſt diligently be obſerued: vve muſt not thinke our ſelues ſure, when wee haue but begun to leaue vvickedneſſe, though, I confeſſe, that is a good beginning of goodneſſe. And <hi>dimidium facti, qui bene caepit, habet:</hi> He is halfe the way, vvho hath well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. But we muſt alſo apply our hearts, our ſoules, and our mindes vnto goodneſſe, and pray the Lord to reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our hearts with faith and grace: for <hi>it is a good thing,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>that the heart be ſtabliſhed with grace:</hi> With ſauing grace for ſinnes paſſed, With preuenting grace for ſinnes preſent, With preſeruing grace for time to come. This vvas that, good S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſten</hi> prayed for, when he ſaid, <hi>Sanctifica cor meum, vas tuum, euacua à ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, imple de gratia:</hi> O Lord, ſaith he, ſanctific thy veſſell of my heart, but firſt emptie the ſame from all malicious vvickedneſſe, and then preſently fill it vvith all grace and goodneſſe. And the ſame S. <hi>Auſten</hi> hath a briefe and fine diſcourſe of the filling and faſt binding of this veſſell of mans heart, alluding to the Parable of our Sauiour, of new and old veſſells, ſaying, <hi>Quando vinum nouum in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres nouas ponitur, cauendum eſt primùm, vt corda munda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, ne infuſum pollueretur, &amp; poſtea vt ligarentur, ne infuſum amitteretur.</hi> In vvhich wordes that holy Father doth warne and admoniſh vs of two things; The firſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing vvith our Text, that we haue care to vvaſh and cleanſe the veſſells of our hearts, before the new Wine of Gods grace be powred into them; and yeeldeth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>ne infuſum pollueretur,</hi> leſt that vvhich be powred in, be polluted: Afterwards giueth like counſell, that when the new Wine of Gods grace is infuſed into the veſſells of our cleanſed hearts, that then we take care for the ſafe keeping and preſeruing of the ſame; and yeeldeth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe the reaſon thereof, <hi>ne infuſum amitteretur,</hi> leſt thoſe graces ſhould be loſt againe; and preſently ſheweth the vſe both of this cleanſing, and faſt binding vp of theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6281:15"/>
veſſells of our hearts, <hi>vt mundarentur à gaudio iniquitatis,</hi> that they may be freed from that ſinne of reioycing in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, <hi>&amp; vt ligarentur à gaudio vanitatis,</hi> and that they may be preſerued from the delights of vanitie. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this difference betweene reioycing in iniquitie, and delighting in vanitie ſaith, that <hi>gaudium iniquitatis polluit, &amp; gaudium vanitatis effundit:</hi> the ioy of iniquitie doth defile and pollute that good liquor which is in the veſſell of the heart, but the ioy of vanitie doth make it runne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Againe, he ſaith, that <hi>gaudium iniquitatis reddit vas ſordidum, &amp; gaudium vanitatis facit rimoſum:</hi> The ioy of iniquitie doth ſoile the veſſells of our hearts with ſinne, and the ioy of vanitie doth make them crany or chinkey, readie and capable to be ſoyled with ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Laſt of all, this good Father ſheweth the naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie both of the one, and the other, when he ſaith, that <hi>gaudium iniquitatis eſt, cum peccatum diligitur, &amp; gaudium vanitatis eſt, cum tranſitoria amantur:</hi> That is ioy of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, when we reioyce in ſinne, and that is ioy of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, when we ſet our hearts vpon things vaine and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie that ſoone fade away.</p>
                     <p>Therefore the concluſion may be, <hi>Quae tranſitoria ſunt, proculdubio amanda non ſunt:</hi> Things vaine and tranſitorie are neuer to be beloued. For which cauſe S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Loue not this world, nor the things of this world, for whoſoeuer loueth this world, the loue of the Father is not in him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And indeede <hi>hinc lachrymae:</hi> here is the woe of all: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can be content to renounce the ioy of iniquitie, but few there are liuing vpon earth, which take not pleaſure in vanitie more then is fitting; one in one kinde of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, another in another kinde of vanitie; ſo vaine a thing is man, ſo vaine is euery man; ſo full of vanitie is euery thing, that it made <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſeſt of all men to cry out, <hi>Vanitas vanitatum, Vanitie of Vanitie, all meere vanitie, and vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 1.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Our honors, our riches, our ſports or pleaſures, that are not well ſeaſoned with the ſalt of Gods grace, are all but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6281:15"/>
vanitie and vexation of minde; from theſe little pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as we thinke) the beſt of vs all haue great neede to haue our hearts waſhed, cleanſed and purged, together <hi>cum magna comitante caterua,</hi> with an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of our ſecret ſinnes, which neuer come within the compaſſe of our knowledge to be repented of.</p>
                     <p>And if euery one haue neede to pray with <hi>Dauid,</hi> that <hi>the Lord would forgiue vs our ſecret ſinnes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12.</note> how much more  neede haue we to pray the Lord of Lords to waſh our hearts, our tongues, our hands, our thoughts, our wordes, our workes, being ſo groſly polluted and defiled with all manner of ſinne and pollutions! And thus much for the Exhortation, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe:</hi> wherein if any ſhall thinke I haue beene too long and tedious, let him know, if ſo long time neede to be ſpent only in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting to ſuch a buſineſſe; how much time had we need to ſpend to act and performe the ſame rightly and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly as we ought to doe!</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="circumstance">
                  <head>The fourth circumſtance.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The reaſon.</note> Now come we to the reaſon, why we ſhould waſh our  hearts from wickedneſſe? Which is in a word, that we may be ſaued. A reaſon of all reaſons to be regarded: for <hi>what ſhould it gaine vs to win the whole world, &amp;c?</hi> And that we may the better conſider of it, let vs obſerue from thence theſe three points.
<list>
                        <head>Three things.</head>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the great patience, mercy and loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards  vs, in wayting for our Repentance, that we might be ſaued.</item>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the care of all good Paſtors in all Ages to exhort Gods people to repentance, that they may be ſaued.</item>
                        <item>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we may here-hence collect and plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that except we repent, we cannot be ſaued.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of theſe three particulars as briefly as I may, and as the Lord ſhall inable me with his grace.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="point">
                     <p>Touching the firſt, To what thing elſe may we aſcribe this ſo long forbearance of puniſhment, for our ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold tranſgreſſions, but to the long patience and meere
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6281:16"/>
mercy of our ſo good and gracious a God? for the earth is wearie to beare the burden of our ſinnes, the heauens are aſhamed of them, and the Angels of glorie bluſh to behold them: Only God in his mercy, and for his Sonnes ſake, turneth the face or edge of his iuſtice from them, that ſo we might repent and be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>But ſinfull man, which either cannot or will not repent, heapeth ſinne vpon ſinne, to his owne deſtruction. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of S. <hi>Paul</hi> giueth good warning, in the ſecond to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4,5.</note> aduiſing that we ſhould not deſpiſe the riches of Gods bountifulneſſe, and patience, and long ſufferance (v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo many wordes to expreſſe Gods Ioue towards vs) adding that this bountifulneſſe of God ſhould leade vs to repentance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But thou,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle (ſpeaking to ſuch deſpiſers of Gods mercies) <hi>after the hardneſſe and heart which cannot repent, heapeſt vnto thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, and declaration of the iust Iudgement of God.</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith likewiſe, <hi>That the Lord is not ſlacke concerning his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
                        <hi>of comming to Iudgement: but is patient toward vs, and would haue no man to periſh, but would haue all men to come vnto repentance:</hi> for it is not mans merit, but of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that we are not daily conſumed in our ſinnes, and as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>Except the Lord of Hoſts, had reſerued a remnant,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.9.</note> 
                        <hi>we ſhould haue beene as Sodom, and like vnto Gomorrah.</hi> Whereby we are alſo taught, that the wicked are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpared from puniſhment for the Godlies ſake; for Sodom it ſelfe ſhould not haue beene deſtroyed, if there could haue been but ten godly perſons found in it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> is willed, as we heard before, to <hi>runne to and fro by the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, and to inquire in the open places thereof, if he could finde a man.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1.</note> And God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe complayneth in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> that he could not finde a  man.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.30.</note> Wherein appeareth the infinite patience and mercy of God towards vs, in expecting our repentance, and ſtaying his hand from puniſhing, as long as poſſible may be. The vſe of this point may be,</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6281:16"/>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> To teach vs to be thankefull vnto God for this mercy, who wayteth daily for our conuerſion, and to praiſe him continually for the ſame; for if we be ſinnefull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull too, then wo, wo be vnto vs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> To teach vs to loue heartily and to make much of ſuch as feare the Lord; for it is for the godlies ſake many times that a whole Citie or Countrie is ſaued and preſerued; and when the godly Magiſtrates or Miniſters are taken away, it is a fearefull ſigne ſome imminent danger may inſue: for <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Moyſes</hi> may preuaile more in the Lords warres with feruent prayers, then the people with all their Pikes. Therefore <hi>Eſay</hi> complayned not without cauſe, That <hi>good men periſhed,</hi> though he knew they were taken away from the euill to come.</p>
                     <p>Yea, <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe cryed out for helpe to God, when  godly men were diminiſhed from the earth;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.1,</note> therefore I ſay ſtill, if thou canſt not thy ſelfe attayne to be ſo godly as thou deſireſt, yet pray heartily, and praiſe God conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually for them that are godly; for God harkeneth, and is attentiue to their prayers, as <hi>Malachy</hi> ſpeaketh.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Malach.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> And  we know that S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>The prayer of one righteous man auayleth much, if it be feruent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> The laſt vſe muſt be to teach vs, to call our ſelues to a reckoning, how long God hath with-holden his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from vs for any ſinne; which long ſince haply we haue iuſtly deſerued to be powred vpon vs, euery man is <hi>Conſcius ſibi,</hi> beſt knowne to himſelfe: therefore follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the counſell of S. <hi>Paul, Let euery one examine himſelfe</hi> for his owne ſins, and let him doe this buſineſſe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he ought to doe, and he ſhall finde little leiſure to prie into other mens faults, which is the fault of all the World.</p>
                     <p>O deare Chriſtians! if this courſe of examination might be preſently put in practice without fauour or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to our ſelues, what a crying of conſciences would there be among vs, ſeeing they are priuie to all our faults? yea, our owne ſoules would exclaime againſt our owne
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6281:17"/>
bodies, and againſt euery member and facultie thereof. One would crie out, Oh my head, for craftineſſe; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, O my heart, for couetouſneſſe; another, Oh my throate, for drunkenneſſe; another, Oh my belly, for beaſtlineſſe; another, Oh my tongue, for blaſphemie; another, Oh mine eyes, for adulterie; another, Oh my hands, for briberie; another, Oh what ſhall become of my poore ſoule, for vſurie: To ſpeake nothing of Enuie, Malice, Pride, Theft, Murther, and Trecherie, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable multitude of all ſinnes, which, like a great floud, haue ouer-flowne all our Countrie, of all which ſinnes we may, I feare me, too too truely ſay, as the yong man did in the Goſpell, though in another ſenſe, All theſe ſinnes haue we commited from our youth: and it is only of Gods mercy that we haue not beene conſumed in them and for them long ſithence. Therefore if there be any ſparke of grace left within vs, if there be any feare of Gods iudgements, if any dread of hell torments, let vs now turne vnto the Lord by true &amp; vnfayned repentance, for the quieting of our conſciences in this life, and for the ſauing of our poore ſoules in the life to come.</p>
                     <p>And ſo much for the firſt point I obſerued, That it is of Gods infinite patience and mercy towards vs, that he hath ſo long expected our Repentance, that we might be ſaued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="point">
                     <head>The ſecond point.</head>
                     <p>The ſecond point I obſerued, was, The care that all good Prophets and Paſtors haue, to exhort vs to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the ſaluation of our ſoules. But vpon this point there is no need to ſtand long. <hi>Noah</hi> and all the Patriarks, <hi>Samuel</hi> and all the Prophets, CHRIST IESVS and all his Apoſtles, all their whole care and trauaile was, to call people to Repentance. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> began with this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Repent, and beleeue the Goſpell.</hi> CHRIST IESVS the Sonne of God did the ſame; <hi>Repent, for the Kingdome of God is at hand.</hi> And after Chriſt his reſurrection, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Apoſtles, and all good Preachers, to publiſh the vertue of his Death and Reſurrection, to this end, as <hi>Luke</hi> reporteth it, <hi>That Repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</note>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6281:17"/>
                        <hi>ſhould be preached in his name among all Nations, beginning at Ieruſalem;</hi> euen the ſame Ieruſalem, though not the ſame people, which our Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> exhorteth here to <hi>waſh their hearts from wickedneſſe, that they may be ſaued:</hi> And elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>Be inſtructed, O Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe of this point may be firſt to teach all Paſtors and Preachers, not to thinke it any diſgrace vnto them, though they do not alwaies ſoare on high vpon the wings of ſpeculatiue Diuinitie, garniſhed with plumes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricke and Philoſophie (though either of them may well attend on Theologie) but ſometimes, if not often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to touch vpon the point of Repentance; for the preaching of that doctrine, did neuer that I reade of, breede any Schiſme in the Church of Chriſt: Mens hearts rather then Chriſt his coate, will be rent in pieces by the preaching of Repentance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And a ſecond vſe may be here, to warne all people to expect and deſire no doctrine rather from the mouth of the Preacher, then the preaching of Repentance, though I grant, ſuch Preachers are called the playne Preachers now-adayes; and indeede they that preach the doctrine of Repentance well, had neede be playne, that is, haue no need to ſpare any Perſons or Profeſſors, nor to colour or couer any vices whatſoeuer. But it is not to heare ſuch playne preaching, that all people flocke ſo much to Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this Age; but it is either to heare newes, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties, or invectiues, that makes many people to preſſe ſo neere this place. But beloued Chriſtian, one thing is neceſſary, namely, the ſaluation of thy ſoule; and no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine more neceſſary for the ſauing of ſoules, then the preaching of Repentance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="point">
                     <head>The third point.</head>
                     <p>And ſo come we now to the third point lately propoſed; that is,  Though there be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much preaching of Repentance, except we repent with it, and by it, we cannot be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>The ſaying of our Sauiour is right well knowne, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 13.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Noah</hi> preached a long time to the old World, and (no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6281:18"/>
doubt) earneſtly perſwaded people to Repentance; but it was not <hi>Noahs</hi> preaching, that could ſaue the world from drowning, becauſe they repented not.</p>
                     <p>The like may be ſaid of Sodom and Gomorrah, where <hi>Lot</hi> doubtleſſe gaue many good leſſons of Repentance; but that did not preuaile with them: therefore were they fearefully deſtroyed with fire from heauen.</p>
                     <p>Now as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſo is it come to paſſe in this laſt Age of the world (as Chriſt foretold) there is now much preaching and calling of people to Repentance, but the not practiſing thereof is ſtill the cauſe, that ſo few are ſaued; for except we repent, we cannot be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>It was the preaching of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> that pricked the peoples hearts in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and made them to crie out, <hi>What ſhall we doe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</note> meaning, <hi>what ſhall we doe to be ſaued?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid vnto them, <hi>Repent, and be baptized e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of you, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of your ſinnes;</hi> for without repentance there is no remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and without remiſſion of ſinnes there is no ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>Further, this muſt be noted by the way, that when we vrge Repentance, as chiefly neceſſary to ſaluation, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude not faith and good workes; for true Repentance is the Child of Faith; and good Workes are both the fruits of Faith, and the true tokens of Repentance. Therefore <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preaching Repentance to the people, did bid them to bring forth the fruits of Repentance, becauſe each tree is knowne by his fruit.</p>
                     <p>And when the Iaylor demanded of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas, What he ſhould doe to be ſaued?</hi> They ſaid vnto him, <hi>Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaued and thy houſhold.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, that faith of his brought forth Repentance, with the fruits thereof; otherwiſe he could not haue beene ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: For albeit it be true, as our Church rightly teacheth, that we are freely iuſtified before God by faith, yet our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6281:18"/>
Repentance and good Workes muſt teſtifie our faith to the world, that it is no dead faith, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, but ſuch a faith as worketh by loue, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth: <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6.</note> whereby it is manifeſt, that the doctrine of S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Iames,</hi> doe not differ touching our free Iuſtification by faith, as many Papiſts pretend: for that which S. <hi>Iames</hi> calleth <hi>a dead faith,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.20.</note> is the ſame faith which S. <hi>Paul</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,  that worketh not by loue.</p>
                     <p>And howſoeuer our Aduerſaries the Papiſts ſlander vs; Heauen and Earth, Men and Angels can witneſſe with vs; that we vrge good workes in our Sermons as much as they, and to better purpoſe then they; by good workes we meane <hi>bona opera benè operata:</hi> ſuch workes as are true tokens of our conuerſion and fruits of our faith in Chriſt, by whom only we are ſaued. And we affirme with Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> that <hi>bona opera non praecedunt iuſtificandos, ſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur iuſtificatos:</hi> Good workes goe not before them that are to be iuſtified, but follow them being iuſtified: for firſt, the perſon muſt be accepted with God, before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that proceedeth from man, be pleaſing to his Maieſtie: And whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</p>
                     <p>We ſay alſo with S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> that <hi>bona opera ſunt viae ad regnum, non cauſae regnandi:</hi> Good workes accompany vs towards heauen, but are not the cauſes of our comming thither.</p>
                     <p>And to conclude this point, which by way of digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I haue purſued thus farre, we all ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, By grace we are ſaued through faith, not of our ſelues, it is the gift of God, not of workes leſt any man ſhould beaſt:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.</note> but yet ſo as followeth in the ſame Text, that God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned good workes, for euery good Chriſtian to walke in. And therefore let euery one that beleeueth in Chriſt, be carefull to bring forth good workes, to teſtifie his Faith &amp; Repentance, without which he cannot be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe of this point may then ſerue, To teach all  people to take heede that they linger not their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and put it off from day to day, becauſe euery houre
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6281:19"/>
they are in danger of death; and if they dye without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, they cannot be ſaued.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> To teach vs all neuer to ſoothe our ſelues in any ſinne, though neuer ſo ſweet, though neuer ſo pleaſing, though neuer ſo profitable; for that is not Repentance that only ſorroweth for ſinne, but that which cauſeth vs to hate all ſinne, and to labour to leaue the ſame to the vttermoſt of our power. In a word, true Repentance, or conuerſion, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſignifieth, is the whole conuerſion of the minde vnto God, with a full purpoſe and holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to denie all vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to liue ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly, ſeeing except we thus repent, we cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; let vs pray night and day for this grace of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for it is not in our ſelues to turne vnto the Lord, for euen <hi>Ieremie</hi> himſelfe prayeth, <hi>Conuert thou vs, good Lord, and we ſhall be conuerted: turne thou vs, good Lord, and we ſhall be turned.</hi> Let vs know, that this is a buſineſſe that of neceſſitie muſt be done, whatſoeuer be left vndone, if we will be ſaued; and the ſooner it is done, the eaſier it is to be done, and the better accepted: put not off thy Repentance therefore any longer, leſt Gods wrath fall vpon thee to thine euerlaſting deſtruction. Thinke vpon the end of thy Creation, thinke vpon the price of thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; it was to this end, that thou mayeſt be ſaued; for this end was Prayer, Preaching, and Sacraments com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and ordayned, that thou mayeſt be ſaued. In a word, this is the end of thy faith, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſaluation of thy ſoule.</hi> Therefore not without great cauſe is it, that our Text ſaith, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſo much for the Exhortation, being the firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall part of our Text.</p>
                     <p>Wherein we haue obſerued, firſt, Who exhorteth? <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie:</hi> ſecondly, Who is exhorted? <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> thirdly, Whereunto? to Repentance: fourthly, For what end? That they may be ſaued.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="reprehension" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6281:19"/>
               <head>Second part.</head>
               <p>Now come we to the ſecond and laſt part of our Text, which is the Reprehenſion, in theſe words: <hi>How long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remayne within thee!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet hauing ſo louingly exhorted vs to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,  by willing vs to waſh our hearts from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; he falleth now to reprouing vs for lingring ſo long our Repentance, ſaying, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you!</hi> Wherein we may obſerue things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of obſeruation, both in the manner and in the matter of this reproofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The manner.</note> In the manner, I obſerue the dutie of a good Paſtor,  and Teacher, who muſt often-times ioyne with Doctrine and Exhortation, Reproofe and Reprehenſion, as alſo the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth, when he ſaith, <hi>Improue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, exhort.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2.<hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Examples of this kinde of teaching, we haue ſtore in all the Prophets, Euangeliſts, and Apoſtles, which being ſo well knowne to all, I ſhall not neede to relate any of them: but in ſtead thereof will take vp a reproofe, which I thinke euery one of vs muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to beare, of what eſtate or calling ſoeuer we are of, either in the Church or Common-weale, that is, That euery one, almoſt, can be contented to heare the Preacher patiently, ſo long as he is in his generall doctrine, and exhortation; or if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he reproue ſinne, in ſome generall ſort: for that which ſeemeth to be ſpoken to all, is taken many times as ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to none. But if the Preacher once begin to fall vnto more particular reprehenſion: As haply when there is great cauſe to reproue the Magiſtrate and Gouernors, of ſome remiſſeneſſe in their duties, that they ſuffer ſinne and ſinners, as Idolaters, Adulterers, Drunkards, Swearers, Prophaners of the Sabbaths, and the like, to goe vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, yea, vncontrolled, and that not in corners, but in publike places, to the great offence of Almightie God, and to the ſcandall of our holy profeſſion: Or when ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times many zealous Preachers taxe others of their owne profeſſion, for neglecting of their callings; or reproue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6281:20"/>
Merchants, and men of Trades, for their ſeuerall deceits, or Land-lords for inhanſing their Rents, or Lawyers for delaying of their Clyents, or mightie Men for oppreſſing the poore, or Noble men, and Gentlemen for ſacriledge, or Rich men for vſurie, or Gentlewomen for their exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue pride in their apparel, or women of lower degree, for following of the faſhion, or any one of theſe, or the like, for their ſeuerall ſinnes whatſoeuer: Oh, then that Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is either too preciſe or peremptorie; he leaueth his Text, and falleth to rayling, as ſome thinke: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, like a paynefull Silke-worke, he draweth his reprehenſion out of the very bowells of his Text, and doth no more then God commands him, <hi>To ſhew the people their ſinnes, and the houſe of Iacob, their tranſgreſſions.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.1.</note> O beloued, if this gentle kinde of preaching vſed in our dayes, be ſo hard to be digeſted, how would you take it, if Preachers ſhould take libertie by the example of the Prophets, to reproue ſinne and ſinners in ſuch playneneſſe and boldneſſe, that they ſingle them out by name, as <hi>Eſay, Amos, Ieremie, Iohn Baptiſt</hi> haue done, though it coſt them full deare for their labour? But they knew their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was with the Lord, and their labour with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> One thing more we may not paſſe vnremembred in the manner of the reproofe, and that is, the vehemencie of the interrogation which our Prophet vſeth, when he ſaith, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Text.</note> for it is a reproofe with a certayne kinde of indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtriking to the very heart of them whom he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth; ſuch force doth the Maieſtie of Gods Word carry with it. When it is preached with authoritie, and in the zeale of Gods Spirit, <hi>It is</hi> then <hi>liuely, and mightie in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>and ſharper then any two-ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſword, and entreth through euen to the diuiding aſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirit, and of the ioynts and the marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and the intents of the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6281:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe drawne here-hence may be, Firſt, to teach Preachers, which are to fight the Lords battell againſt the ſinnefull <hi>Amalekites,</hi> to take courage vnto themſelues, and like <hi>Samuel</hi> the Lords Prophet,  <hi>in pieces,</hi>
                  <hi>To cut and hew Agag</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33.</note> with the ſword of Gods Spirit, and not to be ſo faint-hearted as <hi>Iether Gideons</hi> yongeſt ſonne was, who feared to ſlay <hi>Zebah</hi> and <hi>Zalmunnah</hi> the Lords enemies, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8.20.</note> though his father commanded him ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> A ſecond vſe muſt be to teach vs, that if Preachers muſt be bold to reproue ſinne, yea, to lance the heart of ſinners, with the knife of Gods Law, and to teare them in pieces with the culter of Gods Word; then people muſt be contented to ſuffer themſelues to be reproued, and to haue their impoſtumes of ſinne taken out; for it is for the health of their bodies, and for the ſaluation of their ſoules. <hi>The wounds of a friend are better then the kiſſes of a foe.</hi> And who more foe to man, then they that ſoothe vs in our ſinnes, and ſow pillowes vnder our elbowes, that ſinners may ſleepe the more ſoundly in their ſinnes, as the falſe prophets in old time were wont to doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Hereunto we might adde a third vſe for Magiſtrates, if it would pleaſe them to be intreated to draw out the ſword of Iuſtice, to meete and ioyne with the ſword of Gods Word; for the cutting off of thoſe Hidra's heads; I meane Swearing, Drunkenneſſe, and Prophanation of the Sabbath, that euery day take life againe; ſay and doe the Preachers herein what they can. It is the ſword of the Magiſtrate that can doe more good in one dayes puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for theſe ſinnes, then the Preachers can doe with all their paynes. And albeit we are to bleſſe God, that we liue in ſuch a Land, where theſe ſinnes are both ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the Preachers, and alſo puniſhed by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, when they come to light, yet ſurely many times, too much remiſneſſe in this dutie, may doe much hurt both in Citie and Countrie, where all theſe ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound like a Sea breaking ouer her bankes, which muſt be looked vnto betimes, for feare of drowning the whole Continent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6281:21"/>
And thus much now, for the manner of Reproofe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done with a vehement interrogation: <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Matter.</note> Now come we to the matter of reproofe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of two parts. 
<list>
                     <head>Two things.</head>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is for conceiuing and receiuing euill and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughts into our hearts: for did we not receiue or conceiue them, we could not harbour them.</item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for harbouring and retayning them there toolong, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt, it ſeemeth our Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> playeth  too much the Cinicke, and dealeth ſomewhat too auſtere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his reprehenſions.</p>
               <p>What? Had it not beene enough if he had only repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued actuall ſinnes, whether in word or worke (though I know wicked thoughts conſented vnto, be actuall ſins of the minde) ſuch ſins as might haply haue come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of his owne knowledge; or ſuch ſinnes whereof the World might take notice of; but muſt he come to ſuch ſecret ſinnes, as neuer came within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of mens knowledge, except they that commit them? for no man knoweth the heart of man, but the ſpirit of  man that is within him, no not the Deuills themſelues,<note place="margin">The Deuills know not our thoughts.</note> but by ſignes, except it be ſuch thoughts as the Deuills themſelues ſuggeſt.</p>
               <p>I anſwere for the Prophet, that he doth herein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the part of a good Teacher, and like a skilfull Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon or Phyſician, doth not content himſelfe to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way only outward Vlcers, or coole the heate of a Feuer, with outward coolings, but looketh vnto the inward cauſes of all theſe miſchiefes, and ſo doth labour to take away the cauſe, that the effect may follow.</p>
               <p>Now who knoweth not that the ſeede of all ſinnes, and the Well-ſpring of all wickedneſſe riſeth from the heart of man? as our Sauiour right well teacheth, <hi>Out of the heart proceede euill thoughts, Adulteries, Thefts, Murthers,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.19.</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6281:21"/>
                  <hi>and the like.</hi> Therefore as the heart muſt be waſhed from all wickedneſſe, ſo from all wicked thoughts, which are the originalls of all vnrighteouſneſſe: for the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mens hearts are euill continually, and no man can ſay his heart is cleane; nay, I thinke, euery one will confeſſe, that the wicked thoughts of his heart are worſe then his workes, becauſe either feare or ſhame, want of occaſion, or one thing or other doth hinder the wicked worke, when the heart doth burne or boyle in wickednes; as in luſt, furie, malice, enuic, or the like, which are the maladies of the minde: And little doth man know how much he is bound to the goodneſſe of God, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill doth not know our wicked thoughts, farther then we bewray our ſelues vnto him, or by geſſing at our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions wherein he is not vnskilled.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not neede to relate the opinion of the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men concerning the thoughts of men, euen in wicked things: <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cogitatio de opere illicito, non est ſemper peccatum:</hi> The thought of an vnlawfull thing is not alwayes ſinne: his reaſon, becauſe, ſaith he, <hi>Tales cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones dupliciter conſiderandae:</hi> Such thoughts are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in a double ſenſe, <hi>Aliquando ſunt cum aliqua affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione concupiſcentiae, aliquando horroris:</hi> Sometimes they are accompanyed with affection of Concupiſcence, and then they are ſinne; ſometimes with a thought of horror and deteſtation, and then it is no ſinne. Alſo ſome wicked thoughts are caſt into our mindes by Satan, whereunto we neuer yeeld any conſent; theſe are not our wicked thoughts. But it is not againſt theſe latter thoughts, that our Prophet ſpeaketh; for ſuch thoughts, to thinke vpon the ouglineſſe and fouleneſſe of ſinne, come too little into our mindes: but it is againſt wicked thoughts, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceede of our owne corrupted nature, or ſuggeſted into our mindes by the malice of Satan, whereunto we giue conſent and liking, or the allurements of the World, which we cheriſh and delight in, that our Prophet doth here reproue, withthis vehemencie of an interrogation;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6281:22"/>
when he ſaith, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi> Such wicked thoughts whereof Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>When luſt hath conceiued, it bringeth forth ſinne, and ſinne, when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.15.</note> Theſe wicked thoughts of ours are the Cockatrice egs; which in ſhort time breake forth into ſinnefull Serpents, and muſt be killed in cold Winter, when they ſeeme to be dead; otherwiſe; if we heate them long in our breſts and boſomes, they will bite and ſting vs as bad as Scorpions: Which is one good vſe that we muſt make of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Therefore take we heede how we either conceiue or receiue wicked thoughts into our hearts; for euill thoughts ſeparate from God; and ſuch a heart as is taken vp with ſuch foule and filthy gheſts, the Spirit of grace and of glorie will neuer reſt in.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> A ſecond vſe we muſt make hereof, namely, To keepe watch and ward as well ouer our thoughts, as ouer our wordes or workes; and not thinke we are in a good caſe, if we commit not actuall Adulterie, Theft, Murther, and the like; for our Sauiour ſaith plainely, <hi>He that luſteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Woman, hath committed adulterie alreadie in his heart:</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that hatesh his brother in his heart, is a Murtherer.</hi> And the ſame God that ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> ſaith alſo, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy Neighbours goods.</hi> Therefore, our Prophet, when he exhorteth to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, he willeth vs to <hi>waſh our hearts from wickedneſſe.</hi> And Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned the filthie Phariſes, for that they would <hi>waſh the vtterſide of the cup and platter, but leaue the inſide foule and filthy:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.25.</note> comparing them to rotten Sepulchres, which were garniſhed with an outward ſhew of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but were within full of all wickedneſſe whatſoeuer. Therefore when the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> doth exhort the people to Repentance, and bids them to <hi>ſeeke the Lord whiles he may be found, and to call vpon him whiles he is neere,</hi> he doth not onely command the wicked to leaue their wicked workes, but alſo the vnrighteous their owne euill imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and ſo to turne vnto the Lord; for that indeed is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6281:22"/>
true and ſound conuerſion, when the minde is rectified, and the body mortified to ſerue the Lord. Therefore is it, that the Apoſtle prayeth for the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that <hi>their whole ſpirit, ſoule and body may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> And hereupon ariſeth a third vſe; ſeeing we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to waſh our hearts from wicked thoughts, and haue no power in our ſelues to doe it; therefore being priuy to our owne thoughts and wicked cogitations, which riſe one vpon anothers necke, like the waues of the Sea, we ſhould flie continually vnto the Lord by inſtant and vnceſſant prayer, day and night for grace &amp; ſtrength, acknowledging alſo Gods great mercy toward vs, that doth keepe vs and preſerue vs from running out into all euill with the wicked, ſeeing we haue the ſeedes of all ſinnes naturally in our ſelues, except they be ſuppreſſed by grace, and by the holy and ſanctifying Spirit of God. And ſo much briefly for the firſt part of the Reprehenſion of our Prophet, which is againſt ſuch as ſoule and ſoyle their hearts and ſoules with ſinnefull thoughts, whereby their hearts and conſciences are defiled, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnapt and vnfit for euery good worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> part</note> The ſecond part of the Reprehenſion is for harbouring and retayning ſuch euill thoughts too long in our hearts: <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi> Not that it is lawfull to giue conſent vnto any euill thoughts, or to harbour them in our hearts, no not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time. But as it is ſaid of Couetouſneſſe,
<q>Creſcit amor nummi, quantum ipſa pecunia creſcit.</q>
So it may be ſaid of euill thoughts, <hi>Creſcit amor peccati;</hi> Sinne it ſelfe doth grow and increaſe, ſo long as any euill thought is cheriſhed within vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>The ſeede muſt be caſt into the ground, and take roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,  before it grow vpward to any blade, and the blade muſt grow to a ſtemme, and Eare too, before it blow or bring forth any fruit; ſo the ſeedes of ſinne are firſt ſowne in the heart of man, and there takes roote, before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6281:23"/>
it breake out and bring forth fruit; but if theſe ſeedes of ſinne be weeded and taken away, before the roote haue taken faſt holding, then they rot and die, and bring no more detriment to the ground. Therefore good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt be skilfull in this ſpirituall husbandrie, namely, oftentimes to <hi>teare vp their fallow grounds,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaketh, with the Share and Culter of true Repentance, leſt thoſe ſeedes and weedes of ſinne, which doe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſpring vp in the furrowes of our hearts, doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top and ouer-grow that little grace and goodneſſe which we ſeeme to haue.</p>
               <p>Therefore if it cannot be auoided, but that euil thoughts muſt ariſe in our hearts, by reaſon of our natiue corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <note place="margin">Simile.</note>(for as the earth doth bring forth weedes without  ſowing, bryers without planting; ſo the heart of man doth yeeld forth the ſeedes of ſinne without dreſſing) It ſhould be our chiefe care euen in the ſpring of our yeeres, to weede out, as much as poſſibly we may, theſe ſinfull weedes of wicked thoughts, out of the Garden of our hearts, that the ſeede of Gods Word may grow in the ſame, being indeede the immortall ſeede whereby we muſt grow vp into euerlaſting life. And this is one good vſe that we ſhould make of this reprehenſion. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as this firſt vſe doth ſerue to inſtruct the yonger ſort of Chriſtians, to timely Repentance, before ſinne haue taken too deepe rootes in them: So the ſecond vſe <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> muſt be to reproue thoſe, which together with their age and yeeres, haue ſuffered euill thoughts to grow as old as themſelues, and haue taken ſuch rooting in their hearts, that they are now paſſed weedes, and growne into great Trees; inſomuch that nothing but the Axe of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can cut them downe. <hi>Therefore is the Axe</hi> (ſaith Iohn Baptiſt) <hi>put to the roote of the Tree;</hi> and the fall of ſuch a tree muſt needes be fearefull: for there is no hope of any recouery againe. To this ſort of people it is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that our Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6281:23"/>
How long? a yeere, or two, or ten, or twentie? Oh that were too long; but what ſay you then to thirtie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, fiftie? Oh fearefull! But what if they hold out till ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſeuentie, eightie? O God be mercifull vnto them.</p>
               <p>O deare Chriſtians, let vs feare to grow old in ſinne. <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth God to forgiue him the ſinnes of his youth, and to cleanſe his heart from ſecret ſinnes, which were many of them his euill thoughts. But we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the ſinnes of our age, which were begun in our youth, and continued in our ſtrength, and now dragge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vs euen to our graue. So vnwilling is Satan to loſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of his old Souldiers; he knoweth, they are cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, skilfull, craftie, full of hypocriſie, able to deceiue the world, themſelues and their owne ſoules, but cannot deceiue God, which ſeeth their hearts, and daily cryeth out vnto them, <hi>How long ſhall your wicked thoughts remayne within you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O deare Chriſtians, how ſtrange a thing is it, that we can neuer be wearie of wickedneſſe! that the elder many grow, the worſer they grow, verifying the ſaying of a Heathen, <hi>Rarò ſenes Deos timent:</hi> which indeede may ſeeme to be a meere Paradox; and therefore I will not Engliſh it: for old men ſhould be examples to the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſort, to ſerue God, to loue Religion, to bring vp their Families and Children in the feare of the Lord, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> together with the reſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes and the faithfull ones of all ages haue done.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, we muſt not thinke or imagine, that euill thoughts reſt only in old age, and that this reproofe of our Prophet doth not reach to euery one of vs, to old, to yong, to rich, to poore, to men, to women; for euery one may accuſe himſelfe of this ſinne, that he hath ſuffered his euill thoughts too long to continue within him.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, to conclude, let vs labour betimes to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thoſe ſinfull ſeedes of ſinne, which haue filled this Land of ours full of wickedneſſe, from the Court to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6281:24"/>
Countrie, as <hi>Amos</hi> basket was full of Summer fruit;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 8.1.</note> let  vs daſh out the braines of theſe Babyloniſh Babes and Brats, before they breede vs to greater miſchiefes; for of ſinnefull thoughts come all our ſinnefull wordes, all our wicked workes, all our Treaſons and Trecheries, all our priuie plots and conſpiracies, all our poyſonings and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies whatſoeuer they be: Therefore the wiſeman giueth counſell not ſo much as to ſpeake or thinke euill, no not in thy priuie chamber: and what is more priuie then the chamber of our hearts, where all euill thoughts are hatched?</p>
               <p>The Prophets of God complayne of ſuch as lie muſing of wickedneſſe vpon their beds by night, and in the day time they put the ſame in practice If needs euil thoughts, like ſo many Souldiers, muſt muſter through the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of our hearts, let them only paſſe as ſtrangers, giue them nor bread nor water for intertaynement, then they will not care greatly to come againe; but as the brute beaſt (and euery man is a beaſt in his owne knowledge) will willingly come againe after once he hath beene well intertayned, ſo theſe beaſtly thoughts and affections, if they be any thing comforted or cheriſhed, will neuer tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long away; they are the harbingers of Satan, and like vnto their Maſter; for though he goe away for a time, if he finde the houſe ſwept and garniſhed, that is, prouided for him, he will ſurely come againe with ſeuen ſpirits worſe then himſelfe, and ſo <hi>the end of that man ſhall be worſe then the beginning.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="peroratio">
               <head>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ratio.</head>
               <p>Now God of his mercy make vs all wary and wiſe  vnto ſaluation, ſtrengthen vs with grace againſt all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughts and ſinnefull temptations; pardon vs for our paſſed tranſgreſſions, finiſh ſoone theſe dayes of ſinne, and bring vs to his euerlaſting peace and reſt, through IESVS CHRIST our LORD; to whom, with the FATHER and the holy GHOST, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in moſt glorious TRINITIE, but one GOD in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6281:24"/>
eſſentiall VNITIE, be rendred and aſcribed of all Saints and Angels in heauen and in earth, all honor, glorie, praiſe, power, and thankſgiuing, from this time forth, and for euer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus Deo trin-vno, in aeternum, Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
